so
welcome to parallax lectures i'm your
host thoma mark
um thank you all for showing up
um this is a fairly new format so
let's see how that goes that's the
fourth lecture
we have um you can visit
our uh platform our website
um for updates interviews podcasts and i
just posted the link
in the chat box so tonight my
guest is daniel gertz he's a sociologist
and philosopher and as uh
yeah uh a co-author as hensey freinacht
from the listening society and the
nordic ideology
um randy are you there daniel
good to see you tom how are you i think
it's good
and um i'm very fairly well um
frankly on a subjective on the
subjective scale of states i'm on a
seven
uh uh from over one to thirteen yeah i
mean anytime we're on a seven we should
be grateful life hasn't brought us
greater suffering
uh so let's see if if this
uh talk and lecture can can uh
bring my subjective states to soar
thank you very much that you're doing
that so that you took the time and you
know we we had planned to do the
the conference you know in germany and
that uh didn't work out sadly so
um because of corona and other things so
now we're doing this i'm very
grateful for that and to to um you know
give you the platform to talk about your
great ideas and all of that so um
you're working on your third book it's
called um
six hidden patterns of history
so it's a book on world history
particularly on the
meta memes the great connecting patterns
that
aren't necessarily periods in history
but
but can help us analyze how history has
developed and evolved
right so how far are you it depends
on how you mean by far so especially my
co-author emil has been putting a lot of
work into this he's the historian
but we've fairly recently redefined
how we want to read write the book and
dialogue format namely
the queue and ajf fry night so
um actually we're a little bit starting
from the beginning
um but it's been a lot of fun thus far
right okay so uh
what do you want to talk about so today
i want to talk about
a very a number of very very important
distinctions
about what people
mean when they use the word
metamodernism
people mean very very different things
and metamodernism
i feel in many ways is crippled for this
particular reason
that we're well chasing our own tail a
lot of the time and don't know what
we're talking about
right so hopefully this lecture will
help to bring some specificity and
clarity into that discussion
and that's that's the aim perfect
lecture is based on a chapter that is
coming up in a meta-modern reader it's
going to be called something else they
changed the title several times
but there are chapters by a lot of
prominent scholars of the field
and uh there is going to be one by hanse
frynart
which is titled metamodern sociology
and in that chapter there is also a
definition of the term
metamodernism or some distinctions to
this definition so that's where this is
coming from
right perfect okay so for your listeners
how that works
uh daniel will do like i don't know 30
40 minutes
lecture is that more or less what you're
what you're aiming for
we will chat a little bit about this and
then we'll open the floor for the
participants and i will make them active
participants so they can turn on the
camera
and uh ask their questions and go into
dialogue with you and i i hope that that
would be a lively and interesting thing
so i make you now the co-host so you go
because you have some slides and you
want to um
is that right yes that's correct okay so
okay now
now you're the host and you can go ahead
wonderful
sharing screen
this one um
slideshow from the beginning
what is meta-modernism learning to make
important distinctions and i hope
uh to stress that these are in fact
important distinctions
that i'm not just shuffling around
words here that where um
we have this vast
movement of interconnected things some
of which
are call themselves metamodern and
others that don't at all or don't even
know about the term
but they are somehow connected so um
we'll dive into this and give a few
different definitions
of what metamodernism is
so first the first one
is to claim it's a cultural phase
so uh post-modernism has been around in
society i should mention by the way this
um this lecture is a little bit less
introductory
than our former discussions have been
tom so um
so this is for a somewhat more uh
um well advanced audience who might
already know
a bit about about the topic or have some
preconceptions
um and the first is that it's a cultural
phase
so uh there has been um
um well a lot of ink has been spilled
around this topic of post-modernism the
ironic detachment from modern society
the deconstruction
of its meaning structures the
[Music]
the critical gaze of humanities and
social sciences
discourse analysis revealing power
structures taking a linguistic
turn many of these things feminism is
connected to this in many ways
academic phenomena feminism anyway and
um
as is our things of course within the
arts and
um in the post-colonial theory there are
so many things that are
loosely connected to this large
large structure called post-modernism
and the idea is that after
post-modernism something
else has been happening something has
shifted
in culture in popular culture
and the arts in academia um
in philosophical discourses so there has
been a
cultural phase shift
and if we look then at the term
metamodernism
that's one of the suggestions for what
comes after
postmodernism that it's a cultural phase
of failure recent one
where the irony of
and detachment and critique of the
postmodern
sentiment has shifted
and you have brought in hope and naivety
and progress in a certain sense
albeit all the time oscillating
back to this uh to this postmodern irony
and this has been observed in the
in the arts and in architecture even by
formula and
vandal to dutch scholars and the
cultural theorists who
really pop you did a lot to popularize
this term and give it new
new meaning and and wait academically
and
also culturally speaking allison gibbons
is uh
uh active in that same space and
there are there's uh literally literary
scholars
like alexandra domitresco who has uh
analyzed literature there are a few
books that
particularly uh um
that particularly uh
seem to uh capture this this meta-modern
essence
so infinite jest of course is a title
that comes up a lot here and it's called
a
metamodern novel
greg denver and linda cerelio have
analyzed popular culture and tv shows
and a lot of other things
and looked for this new trend like this
new sincerity showing up
luke turner is an artist himself but he
wrote
meta modernist manifesto uh short
poetic inspiring piece that um
that highlights these
these topics that it's an oscillation
that there is informed naivety that
there is magical realism and so on
so there is a kind of both and thinking
of modernity
and its belief belief in progress and
the truth
and post-modernity with its skepticism
towards these
and it takes many different expressions
across across culture
and in this sense it is uh
metamodernism is an alternative to other
phases
of that cultural uh theorists and
analysts have proposed
post-post-modernism is one we don't we
needn't dig into these
um digi modernism is another one trans
modernism
that one goes a little bit in the
direction of being a new philosophy
we'll get back to that perhaps
performativism also perhaps goes in the
direction a little bit more
being a philosophy but all of these
encapsulate that
that somehow there is something new
going on internet society has some new
cultural dynamics
which were not uh seen earlier
and which should be viewed as distinct
from what we have learned
to recognize as postmodernism in our
culture
and that there are more and more of
these expressions
and certain cultural logics that come
with
these expressions certain cultural
logics
of how um
seth abramson could be mentioned in this
context also
he particularly looks at the cultural
logic of the internet age for instance
how can donald trump get away with
saying different things than other
presidents
surely clearly something has shifted in
the cultural dynamics of society
so that's the most widespread
use of metamodernism and also
the term metamodernism and also the
[Music]
the one most academically established i
should say
now other people have other ideas
more things seem to be going on and
happening after
post-modernism after post-modernity
which brings us to this one it's a
developmental
stage of society
so i put wilbur's integral theory here
i put habermas not because he talks
about metamodernist but because
habermas the great social theorist of
europe
does in his discourse on modernity uh
philosophical discourse on modernity
track stages of development of societies
and
and argues that they have different
certain logics gundogs has
done a different um
taken a different path or view of this
also
great german sociologists many big books
have been written about him
and his work and um
and he bases it on particularly piaget's
the
developmental theory psychological
developmental theory
so the idea here
is that society itself
is shifting towards something completely
different
and all of its institutions are likely
to profoundly change
and the logics of how we govern our
countries
how the economy is organized and so on
um shift particularly
a very important key element here is
that
we're entering into internet society
with a host of other super technologies
of course
but um the metamodernism in this sense
is something different than just a
cultural face
it corresponds more to modernity not to
modernism as an
arts an arts period and then
post-modernist that's another arts
period
but more like modernity going back
even to the uh to the renaissance up to
the industrial revolution up to liberal
democracy
and fully blooming in liberal democracy
that that is modernity and
post-modernity
is the kind of society that comes after
capitalist liberal democracy
so there's a lot more to say about that
i should go on
but that's an enormously important
distinction to be made
and it causes a lot of confusions
especially for the people
who subscribe to this first view
and they hear a lot of people such as
myself talking about a whole
whole new society and they feel well
maybe they're beating a much too big
drum but i don't think
we are actually i think there are good
reasons to believe that
society is shifting in such profound
and uh wide-reaching manners that
um that we can indeed and should indeed
be
thinking about um what this new stage of
society looks like
and this is both an exploratory work
explore what this new stage could look
like
and it's a normative work meaning or a
prescriptive work because
there's a logic to how the stage stages
develop
so it says something about what the new
stage should look like
more on this perhaps later
no it's a meta meme says the third voice
and the third voice says
something quite similar to it's a it's a
stage in society but
a bit more abstract or a lot more
abstracted
it's not the particular society that
first society is modern then it is
post-modern then it becomes meta-modern
rather there have been throughout
history
large sets of memes of interconnected
means or mean plexus
and these we can call meta memes and
they
have an inherent logic that connect the
different
events and processes in them
and each of these are a kind of jet
cultural generator function
which asserts itself first within
certain aspects of
certain parts of society and spreads
from there and spreads
a new cultural logic
so um i mean we saw if you read for
instance
um for instance uh harare's book
um sapiens
he describes how human beings homo
sapiens
[Music]
out-competed other human
species and by by virtue
of communicating in larger groups
around larger imagined worlds and this
was in fact
animism uh the the fact that you could
gather
a fairly large group of people around a
totem around a spiritual
practice and so on um and a lot
around a larger narrative so even though
uh homo sapiens were uh
were uh physically inferior
for in in the european uh in the
european um
climate and so on they could out compete
the the less culturally endowed
um the less culturally endowed
neanderthals and on it went with
actually all of the other
uh five uh uh species of humans
and all were subsumed by homo sapiens so
so
even the first one of these meta memes
is incredibly powerful
well the list goes on and
eventually we have sedimentary societies
with agriculture and a new metameme
kicks into place
which i've called faustianism we have
called faustianism
and um we call it that way because
uh you kind of make a deal with the
devil that
that you get power gods you get
[Music]
well a certain kind of a certain kind of
detachment from nature and humanity
becomes
society detached from nature
and we can can create its own structures
and thus can build more
grander bases of power and fulfill
different desires and needs for
greatness
post-faustianism is the critique of that
of that
crude world um so it's when christianity
for instance
comes to the vikings and christians the
vikings and
their former religion is deemed paganism
and um post-faustianism of course
includes a critique of sheer power
rather the king should be should be
ruling because it's
god's reign or that it's a divine
right something like that um
and there it all points towards
universal truth
this logic is brought to its
end point at one point or another and
uh in comes modernism which says well if
there is a universal truth and if we are
all equal we should all be able to check
that universal truth
for ourselves and
what happens is of course that um
you have a scientific revolution and all
that follows from it
and post-modernism is the critique of
modern society picks that apart
shows that the power structures are
still there that we aren't in fact equal
that
our societies aren't actually rational
and democratic that human beings aren't
rational
and and yeah there's a whole thread
there and meta-modernism comes in
as a pattern that emerges from the
post-modern elements of society
and starts to reconstruct
modernism and post-modernism but also
including elements of all of the former
meta memes so these are abstract and
patterns
so looking at modernism for instance you
can't pin it down to one particular
society
or one particular period because
modernism as um as a
meta meme begins in the arts so it
begins
in in renaissance art
and when you get things like uh
in the in the italian renaissance for
instance you get
perspective and like that the natural
world
is detached from the social universe
so uh from that very move
to view the world objectively to view it
so in a way so that anyone can
can check for themselves from a third
person view of you from
nowhere as it were um
then all of the other modern
institutions follow through the
development of a capitalist economy and
a socialist alternative to it
to uh to the development
of uh liberal democracy and
and full of
full suffrage and so on um
and and human rights and a liberal world
order
so that's the same metamine
but it's not stretched over a very short
period it's over 500 years
and in the midst of that of the growth
of the former metameme at the very top
of modernity you have the birth
of a postmodern critique starting also
first in the arts
long before you had philosophers
post-modern philosophers like foucault
you had
art that could in this sense be deemed
post-modern
because it critiques perspective for
instance and
when when picasso us so very
very um consciously for instance
well so so what the theory is that
can be mentioned that has done re
similar work
uh before and viewed the world
similarly to these uh meta memes would
be jean gibson's looking for these
deep patterns that underlie
history and organize it and he also
notices that there are different
there are different logics that
well one begets the other
and there is a clear sequence to them
so also here comparing to
viewing metamodernism as a face in our
current culture
views it more rid large that
has a bigger and more profound shift and
which were at the very beginning of them
well then there's um
[Music]
fourth answer to the question what is
metamodernism
so it's a rare
stage of psychological development
and that the idea here is that people
develop
as human beings and our values in our
world view
in our personalities and our perspective
taking
um in our sensibilities
and they um they become
modern first and get a modern world view
maybe when you were in high school you
had
more of a mainstream world view yourself
i certainly did and a certain
i had a more materialist view of life
and
many other things and i modernism is
connect to such things as meritocracy
achievement fear and free competition
for instance
rationality expression
through
through achievement expression of the
self through achievement
before that stage you have a stage that
more corresponds to traditional
societies that
where you more try to fit in you try to
follow the values of your society and so
on
uh trying to find one truth and stick
with it
and on it goes that after the
modern stage of development you might
see something
like a post-modern stage of development
or something that would correspond to it
where you can take many different
perspectives
you view yourself more as a relational
being
you value relationships more
you question the the values of your
society
and whether or not it's a fair and free
society and so on
and metamodernism would be the subject
section of those
often fairly privileged and educated and
people who become post-modernists
who takes up a more self-developmental
view
seeing that we develop together that i
am in flux
that uh every
every one of us is uh profoundly
uh profoundly affected by by the
situations we are in so
one becomes more concerned with
co-development and
like i help you develop so that you can
help me develop and you
begin to focus on processes and um
and how much more how
and when than than the actual what
so so there is a there's a
sequence of developmental stages and the
different sequences
uh are presented by by a number of
different scholars so you have robert
keegan suggesting
a bunch of theories that largely
that can that can largely be compared to
this one
that i have sketched and you have
suzanne cook reuter
who has done a lot of
work on on a similar
similar theories could consider a lot
less academically kosher for different
reasons
you have michael l commons who has been
a mentor of my own
who particularly just studies
the complexity of someone's thinking and
also noticed these stages
and he is a new eop dejection so these
psh and stadiums that we go through as
kids where our perspective
and our cognition shifts they continue
into adulthood
his argument and also what his research
shows
and they can also be compared to to uh
to these different stages right and
there are other nymphs that could be
mentioned michael bass such as uh kurt
fisher theodosin
tara fallon claire graves geraldine not
all of them would buy the exact
um or maybe none of them would be up by
this simplified model
that i have presented which builds a
looks a bit more of a caricature image
of these stages
but there is a rich plethora of research
and they seem to be pointing in the same
direction
that later stages are more nuanced more
multi-perspectival
and less identified with the self and
metamodern then in this sense a lot of
people will talk about is this person
meta-modern is that person meta-modern
maybe a while ago it was more popular
say somebody is
post-modern or they are integral in
their perspective
or their modernist or postmodernist or
integral in their perspective
and nowadays a lot of people have
shifted that word integral
in in terms of a psychological stage
to uh to metamodernism
or to metamodern so this person is
meta-modern in their perspective and
people who recognize each other as being
of this
stage will try to find each other and
interact because they find
they have much more in common for
instance
so that's a fourth definition of
meta-modernism a psychological
stage of development and a fairly fair
one a rare one as i said
so likely under a percent of the
population if you're a little more
stringent in the
definitions
[Music]
no it's a certain paradigm
with its own philosophy
well so this is important
that a lot of people when they say
metamodern actually mean
the philosophical engine that seems to
be connected to this
meta meme to uh to this cultural shift
and so on and there are interesting uh
shifts that have happened in philosophy
lately
uh i try to grab six of them here
and highlight them but they're by no
means the the only possible
compilation but there is something
like a profound shift
of world view
[Music]
which afflicts certain people
and then they uh
[Music]
they changed their view of life reality
and themselves and ethics
and society in
[Music]
in abstract but profound way
well basically your philosophy of life
shifts and your
your basic philosophical prop uh
prepositions shift so that's
a fifth one so what are these
well what are these elements as i said
six suggestions here and they should be
viewed as interconnected
so the first is complexity a lot of uh
meta-modern perspectives come close live
close to complexity science and
to studies of octopuses
of self-organization in nature
of um and the interaction of uh
many many loose agents who together
create patterns which are unlikely to
emerge in other
contexts and
there is a view that
unlike more post-modern philosophy
you don't view the world necessarily in
terms of structures and power structures
so much
rather you tend to view them as
different complex interactions
which have um which have
often unexpected consequences
and both desirable and undesirable so
it's also it also points towards a less
black and white
kind of kind of view of the world which
also makes it more difficult
from this philosophical perspective to
take a very strong
position on the classical political
scale etc
going on from there we have a second
element perspectivalism or perspectivism
um which basically says that
well whoever has the most perspectives
when they die wins
that um in meta modern philosophy you're
in the metamodel
paradigm uh always tries to climb out
of whatever perspectives i happen to
have at the moment
and view the world with other
perspectives the perspectives
of people with other paradigms
and other world views the people the
perspectives of
other ethnicities other social groups
other sciences other disciplines
and these together create
these together create um a rich
plethora of perspectives which are
nevertheless
not arbitrarily ordered because you have
a perspective
of the perspectives so you see them
more as emergent properties and
interaction with each other
and the the issue with this kind of
philosophy often becomes to focus on the
emergence where we get to the third one
the emergence and processes
that lead up to these perspectives and
no perspective is
entirely wrong there's always a reason
that somebody thinks something even
uh like even a schizophrenic nightmare
or a conspiracy theory or anything else
there's always something to understand
always a partial truth
um and
well you get to a deeper truth then
by comparing as many perspectives as
possible and getting the best
possible meta theory or meta perspective
but through which we can compare them
we're always building this medic
perspective
a third one uh no the third one was
emergence and processing so
this of course builds us
behooves us to always want to focus on
the best possible processes for truth
seeking for sense making and so on
so you can recognize metamodern
philosophy and this that
it will look for not necessarily
a stable truth it views the world as
full of flows and always always
events always occurrences uh always
uh in flux and for this reason
it tries to understand and see
how these processes and flows can be
reorganized and
and resonate better together in a
greater wholeness
so to speak developmental stages then
yes um i mean some people would
would argue against me here that this
one has to be part of
the modern philosophy and i guess it's
true of all of them that
among men and modern thinkers or people
are part of this paradigm in one way or
another
that uh you'll find maybe 70
um like them and 30 don't for often for
very good reasons
so the the reasons not to like ideas
about developmental stages is of course
they can
lead to judgmental stuff that you
think of yourself as a higher stage than
others
they can lead to
closing down on truly taking
multiple perspectives and they can
you can also uh misalign this
or or misconstrue the stages and that
can lead to catastrophe
for instance if you believe that
capitalist society inevitably collapses
into a socialist one through a
revolution you've made a false
stage theory and um and if you act
according to that stage theory
uh then bad consequences will come out
so you'll also raise the stakes a lot
when you try to uh
to implement developmental perspectives
but the counter argument to that is that
um well if we do
accept them post modern multiple
spectivalism
and a critique of any uh
one great truth out there then
we have already introduced a kind of
stage theory we're already saying
that the postmodern critique
stems from modernity and modernism
and that in a sense that it is a higher
stage
so it is actually less arrogant to
argue that there are several stages and
that there were several stages before
modernity and that there will be later
stages
which will shred whatever philosophy
is being born at this in this day and
age to to bids
and that a lot of people won't be able
to pick up on that
and that there will be clashes of
different paradigms and philosophies
again transpersonal perspective is very
important
um so if we do view the world
as full of complexity many perspectives
um in emergence and always in processes
[Music]
climbing different developmental stages
depending on how you define them
and it also
there's not that much left of
um of the self so when we look
inwards with this kind of philosophy we
see there is no
nobody home there's no self left
and um because hey here i am
in complex co-emergence with the rest of
you
and so there is no clear boundary
between you
and me we still have to set up such
boundaries for
uh for for the sake of social um
functionality and cohesion and of course
i still have my body and you have yours
but in terms of ideas and interactions
and actions and agency
and life courses we develop together
and we are multi um
we are multi-layered each of us
so you can it can affect me by means
of i don't know a smart uh
grounding mechanism on on my iphone or
whatever
and get me to do something i'm not aware
of why i'm doing
and so my agency can come from you and
at the same time i can find another way
to manipulate you or we can
we can bust each other's shadows or we
can
bring each other into into higher
spiritual states and whatnot the point
is
that we've dissolved the eye we're
individuals
and we evolved together
and this brings us actually um to the
last of these
philosophical prepositions on fractality
that meta-modern philosophy or the
meta-modern paradigm this meaning of the
term
closely relates to fractals in many ways
because
um when you
zoom in on anything you tend to not
find an essence use it zoom in on the
left and the right for instance
in politics while there is going to be
left and the right within the left and
the right
and if you examine these
parts closely you're going to notice
that the left
within the right often has a lot more in
common with the left
with the with the left of the left than
with the right to the right and so on
they're going to be so many connections
that you can't place on a simple scale
like the uh like the two-dimensional
scale of um
of uh galton for instance
those little maps of ideological
positioning
rather there it's full of loopholes it's
uh
it's full of the world doesn't consist
of flat planes it consists of doughnuts
you zoom in on one thing and you notice
that aha
what's really going on is that there is
some underlying pattern for instance a
meta meme
and you zoom in on it new self-similar
things emerge
but they emerge in new ways
and this goes throughout all of the
things we've
talked about so fractality applies to
complexity
uh to perspective to perspectivism
certainly
you find perspectives within
perspectives and they resemble each
other
and so on so we are opening up this
large fractal space
where we're not taking a certain
position within the fractal we're
learning
to to traverse the fractal of unders of
our
understanding of the world together
anyway that's in a nutshell that a
modern philosophy and that's
the fifth um the fifth
way people use this term we shouldn't be
confused with the developmental stage
for instance
so how are we doing on time
uh yes uh i i think i can go for a
moment more
so um here we go uh
from the current slide
the sixth meaning it's a movement
so metamodernism is also something
happening out there in the world and
this is also what people mean
when they say the term metamodernism
and there there is a connecting thread
throughout all of these different
movements
reconstruction follows deconstruction
so if post-modern crit for
post-modernist
critiqued the world critique the modern
world
that is critiqued its injustices
critiqued its um critique
its uh inconsistencies its loopholes
cracks in the wall and its exceptions
and so on
it always ends on a question mark it
always asks for the questions
this was also what was deliberately said
by by um
um what what was uh literally said by
by foucault who once he had been
critiquing everything and uh once he was
asked
as the great postmodern philosopher he
was
well you're just against everything what
do you want
and he said you know what there are so
many engineers
and economists in the world who are busy
trying to organize the world
i just want to pick it apart and that
kind of encapsulates
the the core essence no we don't believe
in essences after post-modernism
but a core principle of uh of the
post-modern endeavor
and also of the post-modern sentiment
now we've already
said seen in the first of these
definitions in the phase that we're
reintroducing
magical realism informativity
um a kind of a
kind of sincere irony
a new hope in a way
and all the while knowing that we
after all are probably mistaken and yet
we have to try because hey we're here to
play
and there's this playful element so
um i'm going to list a few different
things
which i feel are connected through this
common thread and things that are
post-modern in a sense then well one
thing is of course
uh the book the listening society
by hanse frynacht um
which tries to reconstruct the
the welfare state and say hey we can
construct a new layer
of uh of politics and a new form of
politics we could look at
other and deeper issues of what it means
to grow as a human being for instance
through the stages of growth
um maybe emphasizing things like
psychological well-being existential
health
um the quality of relationships and
making these
top political concerns
in many ways post-capitalism
[Music]
falls under this or or uh
yeah is under this umbrella as well
because what many meta-modern i mean
movements will uh and settings and
groups will try to do
is not just be against capitalism
they won't necessarily try to
uh view it as something dark or sinister
or like a grim power structure
they will try to create alternatives to
it through commoning
through redefining how
companies organize through policy
proposals
through a new business models um through
um studying the dynamics of internet
economy and seeing how
uh how uh cultural capital and
informational capital takes a
greater and greater role
there are also aesthetic expressions we
mentioned that also in the first one
and we talked about the arts um but you
have
many many different aesthetic
expressions in burning man culture
and solar punk etc which try to recons
to reconstruct a utopian image of the
future
which is nevertheless playful and
ironically helped
which is at the crossroads of fact of
fiction another
another meta-modern slogan
co-development so you have all of these
groups
gathering um around europe and the us
and many other places i suppose
who experiment with new ways of meeting
up
and um seeing what emerges in the room
to put ego issues
and preconceptions to decide and try to
create the best possible processes for
something interesting to emerge
in the interaction itself so that the
interaction also becomes
transformational for the person
who participates
so this is a very important theme i
suppose in all of these movements
co-development you'll find it in the
artistic expressions in the
post-capitalist
and commoning projects
in the listening society of course and
it's kind of politics
and you also have different forms of
secular
secularized religion and democratized
religion and spirituality
so religion and spirituality uh which
kind of were thrown out with the baby as
a baby with bath water
and under modernity and never truly
fully
reconquered under a post-modern critique
thereof even though we have plenty of
post-modern buddhists and so on
um there
there is an attempt to um
there is an attempt to re-um
to recreate these things create new
rituals new co-created rituals
to um to create an embodied sense
of what metamodernism means in
not necessarily without using that term
but this is an important element as well
and
yeah there are many examples for
instance
cynthia's as a movement creating god
under
in the internet age is a is a book that
that works in this direction
well you have also of course
movements to transform organizations and
governance
the government sub organizations a very
popular book
reinventing organizations talks about
teal organizations steel is an
uh color code for a developmental stage
of organizations which would correspond
to metamodern
um so you have all of those things going
on that's also kind of reconstruction
follows deconstruction we have
criticized
the modern society now we're going to
reconstruct
the the organizations within which we
live our work lives
um oftentimes it's a marriage then of
the personal
the political and the professional and
these are reintegrated in new ways they
were differentiated under modernity
and now they are reintegrated it's often
a risky business
and then i should mention that these
movements tend to stem from the triple h
populations
hipsters hackers and hippies so hipsters
are rich on cultural capital um
they're really the embodiment of the
creative class
and they're also rich on understanding
well maybe maybe a lot of book learning
and so on
and find ways of using these things
transformationally
in in the world but they hook up
increasingly with hackers
i am no exception there i'm at hipster i
guess you could say in this
denomination and i work with a
community in silicon valley at something
called the one project
uh who are experts at building software
and i work
formerly also at a and a nike company as
in-house philosopher
and then you have the hippies of course
people who are good at meditation
and all the somatic therapies and so on
and this shows up a lot also psychedelic
practices of course
this shows up a lot in in
burning man culture which is also
naturally connected to the arts
hipster and and silicon valley culture
hackers so these are important
when you put these three together you
kind of have the nexus of where all of
these
all of these movement things are
bubbling up and and
occurring and emerging and where for
instance the
modern philosophy is or different forms
of
modern philosophy are more likely to
take hold
and you might add a fourth fourth age
so you can expand it to from triple a to
quadruple age population to hermetics so
the hermetics are people who are very
interested in symbols
and the occult and in games often and in
rituals and
they're good at inventing these and they
provide a kind of
temple building which is uh instrumental
actually
in many ways for for the others to
gather and
and work together not least if
we are to create new religion and
spirituality
so that kind of exciting capital
encapsulates
where we're at as a metamodernist
movement
and on the surface it doesn't look like
a movement because it's so
it's so widespread and it just points in
all directions
but on the other hand if you look at it
more closely you see
yes reconstruction follows
deconstruction these people tend to like
each other
they tend to understand each other they
tend to be connected
in some way network wise not least so
yes it is a movement just doesn't look
like movements
usually have done historically it's a
more complex movement but their
metamodernism is also a movement and
that's
another distinction that should be made
and not be confused with
modernism as philosophy as a
developmental stage and so on
conclusion so
it is what schwann sean has bjorn
hargens
in 2010 writing about climate change at
that point
has turned multiple ontological objects
metamodernism is a multiple ontological
object
meaning that you imagine a bunch of
circles
a very weird vending venn diagram
and not all of these are going to
intersect
we should view it as the sum of all of
those circles
that's at a moderator's and that's the
most useful way to use the term
then we can nimbly go back and forth
between these six
meanings and perhaps others that can
come up that are meaningful
nevertheless we should integrate these
meanings and we should
uh work across them and back and forth
and
let them uh cross pollinate and so on
but we shouldn't be stuck in one meaning
and we shouldn't
fight the other meanings that's uh i
guess my main argument and
most of all we shouldn't confuse these
meanings on one another then we're
wasting our own time
and the time of one another um
i could end there i'll say two more a
few more words
combining now these six
these six meanings
phase societal stage
psychological stage meta meme
philosophy and movement
it's easy to see that sometimes
something is meta-modern in one or two
of these
in the sense of one or two but not all
of them so for instance you can have a
person
who subscribes to meta-modern philosophy
but isn't
at a meta-modern stage of personal
development
you can have a political leader like
donald trump who partakes
in some of the meta-modern cultural
dynamics that
playing out in society but isn't of
course by themselves as a person
metamodern at all
or would rather be an antithesis of it
or you can have
a meta-modern expression within the arts
and the popular culture
which isn't nominally meta-modern and
doesn't call itself metamodern is
completely
not tied to the med modern movement or
on it goes you can have a modern person
a person of meta-modern
stages of development which nevertheless
doesn't have anything to do with the
rest of these things
and that also brings more texture
to the picture and i hope more clarity
[Music]
that'll be all for for this i'll stop
the share so
we can have a conversation
perfect daniel thank you a lot
for your talk that was fantastic um
very dense and i will soon open up the
panel for all these uh participants
while i'm doing this so um let me just
ask are there
bluntly are there something like
metamodern
morals i i wouldn't necessarily say
metamodern morals
so the the value means that or actually
oh yeah that that's a distinction we
could have made and the value means
visa be there i want one thing i'm sorry
to interrupt you could you make me the
host again
so i can yes of course um how do i do
that you go on on participants and there
you can you can see me
participants over my name and
tomorrow make host
yes perfect so again with the modern
morals
yes meta modern morality or morals
so first of all depending of course on
which of these meanings we look at
the answers are going to be different if
you look at
if you look at something like the phase
just meta modernism cultural phase the
answer would likely be
no actually not necessarily
but if we look at metamodern
metamodernism as philosophy or as
um as a cultural uh
stage of development or a societal stage
of development or ambitime
it's possible to say yes we should
mention though that
morality tends to develop particularly
in this soft the space of the soft
metamies so
modernity largely inherited the
post-palestine morality
you should be against slavery you
shouldn't kill people
uh the the person who governs should do
so for good reason
um and uh many other things
but the point is that we're all equal in
the eyes of god
of course but the point is that
modernity
didn't invent a whole new morality it
just
made real the morality that had just
been
in the clouds as it were or a beacon on
the hill
under post-prostitutes so in traditional
societies
everyone religions would be against
war or at least against the unnecessary
killing and so on
uh but it wasn't until modernity showed
up that you actually got liberal
democracies who don't
who actually don't go to war with each
other
and actually ban slavery and so on
and the same kind of goes for
metamodernism
it builds on the postmodern
ethics which says that like hey we
should
turn around the alienation belt
in in modern society we should
we should make society sustainable
ecologically we should care about other
species
and human beings we should um
be well
we should be critical of the
inequalities or excessive inequalities
of our society
um and and of course
on the far end of post-modernism you
also have an inclusion of animal rights
you should be
including animals in your in your
ethical concerns
so all of these are inherited right into
metamodernism
um and they um
[Music]
the the issue rather is that
metamodernism is likely to make these
things
more real they're not just going to be
minority
voices or critiques they're going to
actually
saturate society so the modern promise
in terms of
morality is to uh substantiate
the promises made of the post-modern
critique
all of those things that were formally
situated in i guess you could say an
ivory tower of critique
and and always kind of a guilty
conscience like the
the intellectuals the post-modern
intellectuals would be kind of like the
priesthood of maternity just like the
priesthood of post-fastiness was the
um priesthood of agricultural societies
always giving us guilty conscience and
stuff
and that's kind of what the critique
particularly on the left has been
now we're going to make it more than a
critique we're going to make it real
so that's that's an important aspect
if we do go take the
philosophy seriously enough though and
we follow through with the
modern philosophy to its endpoint we do
end up with a fractal
ethics and the fractal ethics
[Music]
coordinates the four different
um the four different key components of
meta ethics that are taught in
in philosophy classes so that would be
the social contract
virtue ethics utilitarianism and
deontology or or
ethics by principle
so right now these are competing but if
you apply the fractal philosophy and you
make your fractal ethics you can
actually get a code
that will help you improve um
your your ethical engine as it were and
the ethical engine of society so that's
a promise
of meta modernism hopefully going to be
a future
hansi book that would be the sixth the
fifth book in the hansi series if all
goes well
right so i i i does anybody else
wants to participate or does have a
question now is the chance to do so
do you hear me and can you talk
perfect okay
so so you mentioned deontology like by
by principle so how about uh teleology
is isn't there a mixture always um
and try to find an equilibrium between
those two
uh principles of ethics
um well so yeah that that brings up a
a quite dense discussion and one which
um i don't have
clearly in my mind because it leads to a
fairly
advanced sudoku where you have to put
these four
um these four forms of ethics
wilbur's four quadrants and then you
have to zoom in on each of them and then
you have to see how each of them contain
all of the others but
just saying a few basics deontology
and um and utilitarianism
have to coexist for the simple reason
that the utilitarian
once you have established the principle
uh greatest possible benefit and at
least
possible suffering for the greatest
possible number
is still a deontologist he or she
has to just affirm
that that ethical claim
religiously so all rationality and
alcohol calculation follows
from that first principle and that first
principle is not in itself utilitarian
that first principle is a deontological
principle
so so that's just one way of showing
their interconnectedness
right
yeah questions welcome yeah uh it's more
of a comment
uh now well you can say what you think
about it uh so i've heard the claim
that all
ethics evolved towards rule
utilitarianism
and it seems true to me but i haven't
studied ethics enough
uh because if you started out being
utilitarian you soon realize that
like evaluating every situation isn't
practical so in practice you have to
like
come up with okay what are the rules i'm
going to follow
uh in in each kind of situation
and also if you start out as the
anthologist it's like okay but
how do you pick your rules be the rules
that the
leads to to maximum good um
does it seem right to you uh
i i suppose um
so um so let's see um
[Music]
if we uh um
well yeah we can go on a little bit on
this
uh topic so so let's let's uh say
utilitarianism for instance um
it's already within this philosophical
literature
which i'm frankly not super acquainted
with but it's already within
the literature that you can have
secondary
arguments for utilitarianism meaning
that so
a good heuristic would be uh
you will have greater utilitarian
effects
if not everybody walks around and and
tries to tries to maximize
pleasure and and minimize pain all the
time because then that takes a lot of
calculation and in the end they will
make a lot of mistakes
and then you'll end up with a less
utilitarian
result and that leads us with
to the connection between utilitarianism
and
um and um
virtue ethics and virtue ethics just
says well this is an
honest person this is a humble person
uh this is um generous person for
instance and
um most of the time
it'll make much more sense on an
individual level
to just try to be honest generous and
human unhumbled
than to con then to uh and to hone those
as
qualities which can be embodied and felt
rather than walk around like a computer
the rest of your life and try to
calculate your way
through every situation you you
encounter
um so yes there does appear to be a
secondary
argument there but on a more
fractal level we zoom out and we view
these different
forms of these different forms and
ethics
we can see that utilitarianism seems to
make sense
whenever we've already set the social
contract
and the social contract is already in
place and
we um are
we already have set uh deontological
principles which we can agree upon
and we already agree upon which virtues
we want to foster
in ourselves on one another and then
we use our collective intelligence
on a aggregate level to calculate what
is good and bad and that's where
utilitarianism comes in right
i have a bit of a different questions
that's okay
um uh so i know you know a lot of
summaries of metamodernism coming from
other other thinkers
emphasize oscillation and you touched on
that a bit
um how do you see your you know your set
of
of definitions sitting with this idea of
like oscillation as this primary thing
go forth
and oscillate and i particularly bring
it up because i had encountered
metamodernism
previously and this oscillation thing i
was like okay that's interesting but i
don't really feel a
big grab on it and it wasn't until
coming across oh this developmental
approach i was like oh okay there's
something here
so how do you see those views sitting
yeah
so so obviously there is a bit of a
conflict uh
in because it's a contested term it's
part part of uh
part of why well first of all hello uh
henry it's
a good idea to meet you we haven't had
the pleasure
indeed we've interacted quite a lot
before
so um so um
[Music]
i mean well basically with you there
that to me i don't really skip a lot of
heartbeats over just
just the principle of oscillation and if
i hadn't known about integral theory
and that kind of
that kind of take on what comes after
post-modernism
i probably wouldn't have been super
interested
in in metamodernism
as such i just i would have you know
tucked it away as one more interesting
idea right
the point is that i felt felt that if
you enrich
that oscillation and that
metamoderns has cultural face with these
other meanings with
an underlying deeper engine of a new
philosophy that is emerging across the
board with
a view of developmental stages and yes
there is indeed a
meta-modern and developmental stage and
so on it appears to
fit reasonably well in that
it it jives with this principle of both
and thinking and i thought i
you know in wilbur you have this both
end thinking and
and that's also what i inherited
uh now what i found with the with
the metamodernists who had written about
this term
earlier and from simply the perspective
of
of the cultural phase the arts and so on
uh they had a richer language for it
which better
caught the vibe so to speak um
they came up with magical reels with
oscillation
with informativity with sincere irony
and there was a lot to play with there
and what i felt it was very
integral no it was very meta-modern
so i felt you know they were culturally
much more on the beat
with something that you know i felt
would be salient
and um sustainable culturally
sustainable in our day and age so
i felt if you take that metamodernism
stuff and you
put it in integralism and vice versa
uh you can get the best of both worlds
particularly
you get a kind of design intervention in
in uh
metamod in integralism which
had many weaknesses but one of them was
aesthetic you know that metamodernism
had all these corny um
well well you know these very new agey
images uh and and it just doesn't speak
too much
most people it particularly just speaks
to the people who
um who can relate to those spiritual
experiences that are being uh
portrayed and and by the way it also has
a difficulty living up to it because
it's not ironic enough and it's
presentation of itself
um which also makes it prone to all of
these
uh cases of hysteria where where people
uh over invest in well
gurus and so on and
cast post modernism green is the central
adversary
um is i think yeah integral has its own
aesthetic
and and i agree that a modernism and
particularly particularly sincere irony
i think is one of the
one of the things that grabs me a lot
okay that that that makes a lot of sense
yeah yeah how are you how you how you
got to that particular
synthesis yeah and thanks henry is it's
just
sometimes i like superposition better so
but at the same time i feel ashamed
using it because i don't know so much
about quantum
theory i don't know what you mean but
um but superposition um
two things are entangled they're
interconnected
it's in two places there's
a non-locality you can er
you can manipulate one thing and the
other thing um
changes so it's in two places at the
same time and we need to
be like oscillation sounds like you have
to hurry back and forth
i like superposition better because it's
more static that
you can be deep in the irony and the
deeper you go in the irony the more
sincere you can get
so you can write an outrageous book
where you're super out where you're
super
um you know rude and and
and shocking and everything and because
you do that
you open up the space for being very
very very sincere
this is what i really want this is what
i really feel these are my real hopes
these are my real concerns
and if i just put those out there it
just joins a million other voices
um it doesn't uh stand out aesthetically
and most of all it doesn't appear well
this and this goes back to
post-modernism really
post-modernists will always
[Music]
distrust or at least the dark poems not
not the light
almost like the marxist types more or
academic types more they will distrust
any true believer right right so you
have to be
and and what i kind of found
and not just myself other people too was
that when
when you're really deep in the irony you
can become the true believer just comes
in through the back door
and and without being tunnel vision
because you're
in a tunnel but it's a fractal tunnel
and it opens you up
closing you down um so so that's
uh actually yeah superposition is better
um but i realize i'm probably making a
fool out of myself
before i i'm not qualified to say
so yeah i like i like super position i
also like uh i also like
um productive tension i think is the way
that i think about it like you do have
both of them at the same time and
there's an interplay
but yeah i don't like this they're going
back and forth
yeah but thank you
and they even actually write this uh i
think from
there and vandakar they really write
about different islands which you
literally hurry back and forth between
um and and it
sounds like hard work
yeah yeah i also agree that like the
the framing of the listening society
sets you up so by the time you get to
the vulnerability of the state and depth
chapters
i in particular i found that that was
like okay now we're ready to do a do a
dive in there and you're
you're you're primed to accept the
the vulnerability and sincerity because
you you know that you know that
the the the ponzi is in on the joke too
on the
yeah the ironic joke of the world so
yeah
i also want to point you uh henry to
brand cooperats right now
thanks brent thank
can you ask a question hello
tim please go ahead yes hi yeah
this is my second outing this week
online so uh you know i've been a bit of
a hermit the last few years but it's a
pleasure to meet you face to
face online and um
i i i i have to admit i was at least one
notch behind you on the hierarchy of
subjective well-being this evening and
you've got me up at least a notch up to
your level so thank you for that daniel
um my question was well i really wanted
to allow
you to elaborate on on something in
particular because
most of those six forms of metamodernism
and metamodernity that you're outlining
work to do with answering the question
what's next
but hansi picks up on another
greek word the the to do with the mataxi
metasis and in other words what's in
between
the kind of concepts of in betweenness
so i was hoping you might just be able
to elaborate on the importance of
the metaxic as well as matter in terms
of going beyond and
saying what's next um well a
great pleasure to meet you also tim
another person i have
interacted with a lot and never had the
pleasure to be
so um yes first of all
uh ataxia and so on is a stronger theme
than in the cultural uh theorist
metamodernists um so attacks metanoia
and brent cooper has done actually more
working he'd like me
perhaps like say a few words about as
well i notice he's here
um but um
just my own two cents um
they they look at metamodernism more
in this term like acids and that in
between as a transition
and so on as in between this is a very
important
part of any relational philosophy which
we could have also put up there with the
um with meta modern philosophy uh
term um and um
i i feel that it also makes sense to
talk about what the next
stage that we want to construct looks
like that being said we are in
in between us right now like we've never
been before we're in ten different time
types in between the in-betweeness and
ones
and so it is important and just to say
something about
the the particular historical moment um
all of this relates to different
theories of change of course
uh the the most prominent one is
well perhaps the the broken institute
theory of change
which which says that
one paradigm one big
system uh matures
and then become you you see many little
uh inventions of alternatives showing up
and as the other one
starts to crash to under its own weight
then
it becomes more uh president it becomes
more pressing
uh for for these new agents to uh to
take more and more responsibility
connect with each other
and all of their work begins to
congeal and they learn from best
experiences and so on
one thing goes down the other thing goes
up right and
we're at the we're in the steep hall
of modernity and then we're in the rise
of
something new i would call it
metamodernity and post-modernism then
is not in itself a stable phase it's a
critique of modernity
um and it does and it showed up under
modernity's let's say technological
regime whereas
metamodernism is particularly an
infinite phenomenon
and particularly linked to that social
logic which is probably the sociology of
the future
so that's one way of seeing it another
way which i
uh in many ways prefer is that history
involves movement and institution
and so it goes back to um sociologist
albaroni
um alberto alberon or something and he
uh he says well that
institutions eventually crumble and then
there's this moment
of uh just rejoicement and joy where
everything is up
in the ear and it's like falling in love
everything becomes liquid for a while
before it congeals again
um but there is also a sociological
theory called
revolution and counter-revolution uh by
sima lipsid
and the counter-revolution is
the reaction to the revolution because
the revolution
given that it doesn't build
unestablished structures
it contradicts a lot of the social
orders
and it doesn't build on a lot of
experience
so it's prone to failure and
overreaction and uh
and all of other well just mistakes
just a lot of mistakes uh so when the
revolution
does go wrong which it inevitably does
which is kind of what has happened with
our
postmodern fatigue society um
there is a counter reaction just like
after the french revolution
like in the early days of the french
revolution people were walking around
naked down
downtown literally and having sex with
whoever and
like things were crazy and after a while
uh heads start rolling and wars erupt
and then boom the old order
reestablishes itself
reacts very strongly is strongly
reactionary
um it throws out all of that
new garbage whatever that was and tries
to continue where things were
but they've also picked up a bit of the
social dynamics of the new world
uh so eventually though it is
when the counter reaction or when the
account
revolution is defeated on its own terms
because it never has
it doesn't look towards a new
equilibrium state it doesn't look
towards the future tractors
so inevitably it's doomed
um but it's going to win first
um to the excesses of the revolution
and right now we're in that counter
revolution which is
what we're seeing across europe uh in
the united states in world politics at
large
um and also in the cultural dynamics of
our day and age
uh so and it's often during the
counter-revolution that
most the worst atrocities are committed
unfortunately so we're looking probably
towards a fairly grim time
which makes our seeding forms
that we um come up with now and try on
now
all the more important for for the time
when they have matured
and the counter-revolution has run out
of fuel and shown that
it doesn't actually produce a much
better society
um and yeah
that's kind of the in-betweenness
historically speaking that i feel we're
in right
now so we're in fairly dark times
hopefully that brings everybody down a
notch against subjective state
i've gone up to 13.
brent do you want to say something on
metaxi and metamodernism and
stuff you've written a lot more about it
than i have
sure thanks um i like your presentation
uh you should you should include me in
there somewhere
um but uh no one thing i like to
um you know kind of introduce kind of an
injunction right is like
these missed sources that i dug up like
borgman
and um
oh god i forget their names
um there's there's several though the
three or four from the 90s particular
and a couple from the 2000s that just
aren't touched on
and then you know my recent article on
hyper modernism right i pivot that way
because it's this parallel
discourse and and
um let's say vermeulen and vandenker are
they just chose not to pursue any of
that right i think that's
i think that's a mistake there's a lot
of interesting stuff there so it begs
the question of today
how how we all came to this topic right
and and discuss it
without this prior context and
and it's not a bad thing it actually it
actually expands
becomes more fractal because
because we get this new research and it
dovetails with the idea of
historicity which is in in both
metamodernism and hypermodernism
so we get to examine the past 30 years
as a period right post-col
post-cold war is when both of these
phases really began
and then of course it's more
crystallized after 2000
with the internet and 911. so i think
i think these have been missing pieces
of the puzzle
but of course like daniel's framing is
very comprehensive
uh excellent kind of six dimensional
meta theory pretty hard to
to undermine that it's very robust
but i but i try to i try to historicize
it right and also problematize
the way people come to metamodernism and
misunderstand it
as you touched on right and so so
there's different um
you know people with different
ideologies that they're still
trying you know they're trying to level
up and trying to get away from
these past ideologies or political
alliances but they're still
trapped by it um
so yeah i guess that that's all i wanted
to
kind of unpack but if anyone has any
questions on that i can go deeper
yeah thanks friend
well well i had a thought coming up uh
why um in your lecture
when you mentioned autophases right as
one of those engines
um so so could you elaborate a little
bit on that of
the relationship between metamodernism
and autopoisons if there's
any how does it play out because that's
a fairly
interesting concept in general
and you know nope you get my question
yeah so so uh first of all uh
i'd like to uh make a caveat that i'm
not
er i'm not necessarily uh
um
a huge subscriber to all the polices
as as it's often used
namely as self-organization and
it to be contrasted with than
than engineering and control
because i think that might be a bit of a
false dichotomy
if you zoom out we're never quite out of
self-organization of course you have
agents in the world
they try to control themselves and their
environment uh
that's engineering but if you uh
crisscross
all of those different uh perspectives
and
all those different agencies you do have
a self-organization
the point is that the self-organization
can can then
land on stable equilibria like like a
functional
ecosystem or it can have some agents
taking too much control
and not having feedback processes which
regulate them back into what is good for
the wholeness
so for instance human beings get super
much control
after we develop all these technologies
and organize ourselves into modern
states
and then we make um
well huge irrigation projects and
whatnot which then disconnect from the
self-organization that exists in
local communities and also
might fail to integrate the systems of
nature
and so they are huge failures sometimes
and
cause incredible damage so so that's
i mean that kind of takes the boat and
there that yes there is a critique
against
against engineering social engineering
included
but at the same time we can never fully
disentangle the two concepts of agency
and planned
engineering which just means
manipulating one's environment
and oneself and and self-organization
there's not like this pure innocent
autophages and this
uh evil control freak of an engineer
on the other hand what what does exist
are the feedback loops which are too
slow or too disconnected
so that things fall out of autopleases
in terms of a certain unit of analysis
for instance an ecosystem so right now
humanity has is
a species on earth among many others and
we have self-organized in societies
but the feedback processes from
from nature are too slow so we don't
regulate back
when we harm nature because it harms us
back too slowly and too
regularly for us to naturally
regulate back and then we have to
make forecasts about the environment and
start talking about it
but our whole institutions and so on and
habits and way of life are entirely
disconnected from that
feedback process um so
that being said yes metamodernism
as a sentiment and also as a philosophy
looking at
complex systems and self-organization
uh looking at multiple perspectives
looking at emergencies and processes or
for having those
as its dna as it were um
it lines up with autophagic theories
such as we should identify with a deeper
perspective with a wider perspective or
a range of wider perspectives
so that we include animal rights and
the ecos and the biosphere so that we
can become
a constructive part of gaia's expression
rather than a cancer on
lovelock's gaia system for instance
and also in terms of organization then
we will try to maximize the autonomy
of uh and the sovereignty of each
individual and then each enclave and
cliff and then each
part of the organization and you'll try
to
link them to as many other relevant
stakeholders as possible so that it
doesn't get
trampled by the hierarchy of the
organization
and which is an adequate poetic
sentiment or principle but
to get to auto pleases you have to
be fairly engineering uh you have to
take up
you have to be playful you have to make
suggestions and
this is a difference then between a
postmodern sentiment
uh which could still be aligned with
autophages as a kind of
that's just viewed as kind of so
impurity principle
versus uh we're always part of the
autophagesis
and our engineering attempts including
social engineering tense
become um naive informativity
and become proto-synthesis actually
like we know that these suggestions
might not work but we have to try them
because we have to develop together
right
right yes yes i mean this
and and of course i was thinking uh
uh uh about autopsies as an
intrinsically
connected part of psychology and uh uh
outer places of consciousness and
developmental stages
you know because you can't really think
developmental stages up to a point
without thinking about autopoaces
and how the um how the how the
consciousness works and
and the psychology and so like even in
simple models like keegan and
and self-authorship and
self-transformation so there's like
this element of autopsies come into play
and how we use our consciousness you
know and it's like
it's very very similar to metamodern
modernism as a as a psychological stage
isn't it
yes i i do believe it is and actually
in when we look at the
different meta memes as
when we look at metamodernism as a meta
meme it's a
certain cultural um
generator function so it generates
culture of a certain kind or or just
actually the same is true of
post-modernism so for instance
look at the painting over there it's not
impressive
i made it a bunch of years ago
nevertheless you can look at it
and see that is this painting
from the 1700s
and you can just answer no and it
doesn't have anything to do
with my developmental stage as an artist
it's just the fact that i live in a
postmodern world
so uh flattening things up
and uh and making a dreamy symbolical
landscape which is maybe a sea maybe not
maybe a moon maybe
it's maybe a son who knows
and there's a lot of expressed emotion
in it even though
it's not very well expressed the the
that very thing
couldn't couldn't be conceived
if you're not in the post-modern
generator function
um and and this is so so they
they are kind of auto poetic systems in
and of the moment
in and of themselves has generated
function and the same
goes i believe but i can't prove it
for how our for how our
mind works meaning that uh
well so let's say somebody has
a thousand different propositions that
they believe in
which link up together and they
all um they
all support one another at least partly
and they uh together they make up a
post-modern world view
along comes comes your meta-modern
friend and says a meta-modern
proposition
and it contradicts a thousand
presuppositions that you already have so
your gravity just pulls it down
and falsifies it it's just like there's
no way this one can be true because then
all of this one these 1 000 different
things that i uh
that i already believe would not be true
rather than for for the
self-organizational system of the mind
to shift
you have to shift and
500 or more of those little little
nodes or stars on your sky uh
into new constellations and then they
link up and then they start
because the mind is always the process
always doing things and then
they start doing things in new patterns
and that's
a self-organization um
these uh and interestingly then i don't
know if others have noticed this but
when i talk to you guys for instance
and and a select crowd like this one
the words just kind of flow you know i
just you just
ask me all sorts of difficult questions
i come up with some kind of answer
and and i kind of feel supported by
like just the vibe i'm in by the
presuppositions of the crowd
well then i go down to i don't know my
old colleagues at the university or my
family
and i try to explain just
something i view differently and i just
can't find the words
right because well trans personal
perspective right but
that like i don't have the other
points to link to i can you know i can
i can tinker a little bit with one or
two points and say wouldn't it be
interesting if or blah blah blah but
but by and large i'll find i have a
whole like
other part of me which just
doesn't there's a barrier i can't breach
and i can't go
past it and i just can't speak and even
if we go deep into discussions i
i can't come up with anything to say and
that would be metamodern
so then i'll stay within a postmodern or
modern uh
mindset and i'll also not be able to
think of thoughts
while i'm going there a little bit but
the thoughts will be
farther away from me so they're also
transpersonal they're also in in the
field so to speak right
which again i mean speaks
a lot to this thing about viewing
metamodernism
as a movement that as a movement on a
deep level even though we're not
calling it metamodernism necessarily and
there are all these interconnected dots
that
don't seem to have much in common
nevertheless
um you can enter into these different
fields
and and kind of interact a lot
along this self-organizational logic
that you
that you experience and also the
embodiment becomes different
um you also you just become a different
person like you
like your metamodern self or whatever
which is also a big part of why i had to
isolate myself
uh writing the books by the way um just
to get away from all the gravity
that where i couldn't access that stuff
right
as your neurology goes into a bit of a
stress response if you're surrounded by
this different perspective
you know that it's things aren't going
to land the right way
yeah i guess that could be a big part of
it uh i
i mean hey i wish i was a bigger person
than that and could live up to
well that's just more perspectives and
i'll play with it but uh but oftentimes
i do
feel a bit of distance and well as you
age of course you
uh you learn to live with it and then
you accept that for what it is and then
you
find well there are many ways to relate
to other people and once you've kind of
had your fill
with meta modern code and culture and so
on
then it becomes more okay that people
just
different and we have different settings
to be in right
yeah i'm also thinking a bit in the in
the cultural somatics frame
of kind of what kind of attachment is
there between the
the emerging meta-modern culture and the
postmodern or modern
cultures and it's not a secure
relationship at this point right there's
a
there's not enough of an established
base particularly if you're outside of
your supportive context
to really have that kind of secure
attachment neurological relationship
with a different cultural context around
you right now
and and that's i don't know as you know
i'm very fascinated by this cultural
semantics uh
frame and like what kind of kind of
cultural interactions can be modeled
that way
yes uh i i agree uh
and i think um i think um
that this was something i was
talking to uh jim rutt with on his
podcast
uh that and and this is connects back to
this
fourth age the hermetics right
um that there is a particular role for
this category
within uh uh within the metamodernists
and they're a little less outward
bound so hipsters engage with all kinds
of stuff
around them as do of course hackers and
hippies as well
whereas introvert types are often a
little bit more
the the hermetics and um
and they have a particular role to play
when it comes to creating
well meta-modern temples where we can
charge
our batteries as it were culturally and
and
embody stuff better and and just kind of
feel supported by
my community and culture uh which feels
a little bit esoteric but just a little
bit just ironically esoteric right
you shouldn't actually have anything to
hide right
but but sometimes it helps to have a lot
of space
yeah and and so some interesting rituals
and these can be reinvented
like continually but we need to probably
as a movement
become better at that and i um i'm
optimistic that i see
more and more of this tendency at the
same time of course is a fairly
dangerous path to walk because hey then
you get into all the stuff like
well esoteric stuff basically but when
stuff that's difficult to explain to
other people
psychedelic practices not least and
and this um
this creates um this can also create a
chasm
or and actually also slides into
things that that are connected to
esoterism and occultism
for instance far-right thinking where
you feel like whoa i felt the strong
energy so let's
make this strong energy take over
society
not not a good idea yeah yeah
i i find i find some hopeful things in
the uh in the immersive theater
uh scene the interactive theater uh
festival practices
that are pretty big here in in san
francisco or were when we could
run off and have big interactive groups
of people running around in
in costumes and and and story lines
uh but that's that's kind of uh
uh a a supportive ritual that seems to
it brings in both the irony and the
sincerity um you know it's people
looking for authentic connection but in
the context of
some sort of crazy plot line that we've
all agreed is real for the weekend
um that's that's the kind of place where
i see some ritual
possibilities emerging this appears to
be a
recurring theme actually so so that's
interesting
uh i i noticed you were waving michael
yeah i was uh more curious what you said
like
when you show up in a setting like this
as you met a modern self and
stuff i've been noticed certainly now
that we're doing in digital contest
on a screen in zoom here but still you
can summon your metal modern self when
you are in the presence of faces you
think are
meta modern and what's going on there
really i've been noticing
it all summer and fall when i'm in the
circle some course
you i just show up as a a more me
[Music]
so so i think henry might have said part
of it that
uh that well if we feel that what we're
going to say isn't going to be super
well understood
and maybe what we feel also when we feel
the kind of expression that we're making
is going to be misunderstood and
misrepresented
and then we get a little bit nervous and
nervous
shuts down shuts down complex processes
right so that's i'm not on a very
simple visceral level that could be it
um
but um but the other part i really think
is
uh like well we're social beings we're
interactive beings
and interactive beings uh so that like
you say something it prompts me to do
something
and so uh like yeah
like a dance or whatever right so uh
you will throw me balls which
for me aren't curved balls i can
catch them they make sense to me uh
i can feel i can play with it we get in
a
more playful mood and and
like there are enough uh
there are enough
presuppositions shared for for like
a breakdown of the conversation not to
be imminent
every 20 seconds so
this helped we help each other to
stretch our minds
into more complex modes of
thinking and being and now of course
um the critique of against this is that
when we stretch our minds and do more
pretty into more
complexity we also disembodied a little
bit
uh because then we're in our heads
and i have to say i'm i'm not that
scared of um disembodiment
for uh for a little while here and there
right
uh because well i mean sure if you get
stuck in it
and uh you get less sensual or
less sexual or less less uh
alive or something then that's a problem
of course
or you forget to tune in your feelings
and all of that
but for a while it's okay to be in our
heads and
play with ideas and then it's an
inherent tension
in meta-modernism that because we're
trying to go very very
uh complex and we're trying to go you
know spiritually deep and high
um we hear actually the word oscillate
henry
might be better
we inherently have to be good at
oscillating between these
and ideally we could get into
quantum superposition sorry linda
linda wrote in the chat that she will
explain what it actually means at some
point
uh but um but i ideally we could really
be in both and maybe in the future we as
individuals and we together will be
incapable of that uh integralism claimed
to be that
um but in many ways it's it failed
particularly on the complexity of the
stringency side
and the depth and community and
communion would would trump uh
stringent thought and and clarity and
complexity
right so so we have to be defenders
of both of these sides i guess um and
and that's
i guess that's a part of the tension
that never leaves us
that even when we are together right
i think daniel if i could just come back
on back to my question
on um i don't know what my question was
the
the in betweenness in relation
yeah the taxi in relation to what you're
saying now because
i think behind my question i sort of got
it into my head that somebody who's kind
of meta modern
is likely to have a greater facility for
kind of
operating at different levels engaging
with different
codes and even mediating between
people who might come from you know
different ends of the spectrum almost
and
that cam in my personal experience that
can be quite a dangerous situation i
mean not that i'm
setting myself up as the next messiah to
be crucified but
you know if you're if you're kind of
playing not it's not a game but play
playing being in between for the sake of
kind of sharing things that are going to
be received by people
it can be quite dangerous
agreed but so are all other positions
um so what we argue in
the nordic ideology is that modernists
are going to win
in the long run and they're the opposite
of populists because populists
and they go for local complexity and
thus towards the lowest common
denominator
so uh a lot of people are bothered by
the presence of a lot of new arabs in
swedish society so the populist party
are going to say well how about not iris
and yeah stuff like that right
uh whereas metamodernists go in the
opposite direction and say
hey we're gonna do so complex stuff um
and be so nuanced we're gonna bore you
all to tears
uh you're not gonna be wanting to listen
to us
so they'll always they'll always only
attract uh
in terms of votes versus popular support
a lower
uh a lower lower portion
but because uh these processes
that are created in that modern circles
and so on
manage greater complexity they also
manage to
imbue more perspectives
and then they can uh traverse what other
view
others view as flat
um scales or one-dimensional scales or
two-dimensional scales
and they can uh well
walk through the third dimension and pop
out on different places
and as such they can have uh more
weak ties and that's a powerful uh
uh theory in network theory that weak
ties
can can help out a lot uh and
in those weak ties they can always offer
interesting counter perspectives
so a person on the right will get
interesting
will get interesting tips on how to
counter close modern arguments for
instance
a person on the on the left will get
interesting
uh critiques into this psychology of the
right and so on
um and as such they can be a little bit
friends
with a lot of people and as such they
can have bridging functions
and they're going to then be viewed as
well a bit too meek a bit too
wobbly a bit unprincipled uh they're
going to be
never be anyone's favorite but they're
likely to be
the least hated alternative so my
left are gonna hate them a little bit
less and they need libertarians
libertarians behave a little bit that's
when they hate the left
and so on so you and this is also a
theory in
uh network science uh of uh the string
of non-negative ties
and because you then build
the greatest wealth of non-negative ties
and you
uh garner the the most the greatest
concentration
of perspective taking and the greatest
capability of coordinating perspectives
um then
[Music]
chances are that fairly small groups
can influence society a lot
by means of having this unique position
now
and what i would like to see happen in
the world what
isn't happening yet is for the creative
class or the quadruple age populations
to be
come more conscious of themselves as a
class and society
which are distinct from the interests of
the middle class
middle class want more or less to keep
the status quo and so actually does the
working class
uh in many ways i mean some
redistributions differences and so on
but
um but then the modern uh
quadruple age class have a distinct
uh class interest in a more deeply free
society
where you are liberated to you know go
off and do your crazy
uh projects and experiments uh which are
highly likely to fail
but in accumulation
canada will save the world right
and but the middle class won't have it
they don't want to pay for that with
their tax money in terms of
ubi and so on and then there is an
alliance and between
metamodern is since the creative class
but also the precariat
the people who don't fit in and the
categories of
worker entrepreneur
and and so on uh so there's of course a
revolving door if you
live a risky life for the creative class
you can land a preterity it has happened
a lot of us um and um
and then what both of these groups need
is a more listening society which
empowers
sovereignty and doesn't let you spend
your
unemployed days uh you know making all
of those
applications uh and
you know jumping in so many hoops from
the from the authorities and
and uh and the companies and
so so uh i i do see
a separate class interest there um
which is orthogonal to to the
to the classical scale and i think that
before it has you know
gotten its support structures it feels a
lot more dangerous
but actually it's one of the less
dangerous positions in society
because uh when push comes to shop and
things uh
there is a lot of turmoil uh we'll have
uh allies and friends and perspectives a
bit more all over the place
um which i mean the chameleon is
is often safe and the the the octopus is
often safe
right
yeah can i just ask you a bit more about
the precarious
that you mentioned that because i mean
if you if you follow
um guy standings analysis he's talking
about the development of a kind of class
consciousness
there but but three very disparate
groups in society in western society
that are actually
tend to be antagonistic towards each
other so you've got the descendants of
the traditional working class you've got
ethnic minority immigrants and you've
also got
kind of highly educated younger
people who don't find any employment
commensurate with a kind of
you know their complete levels of
complexity
so so what you're saying now about a
kind of quadruple
h class consciousness developing i'm
just
interested to know how that would help
what guy standings talking about in
terms of engaging with the precarious
yes so i realized we're on times i'll
have to uh respond
very quickly uh but i'm not a super fan
of uh
of the chi stamina's precarious uh
theory because i don't view it as
realistic
to the the fundamental um
uh alliance as realistic
um and and in fact since you published
the book you haven't seen these uh
this new dangerous class emerging really
um
and what what you see in on the
uh in the cop like
what what my sociologists colleagues
have studied in
um and their protest studies and
demonstration studies they see that
young people show up at these
protests and demonstrate what uh
what we would call pomos the the
postmodern population
um and um i i think it's a
bit of a left-wing wet fantasy that um
the working class would align with all
of these new immigrants
who are competing for the same jobs and
at the same time their national identity
being perhaps
their primary source of pride that they
still have if they're less
privileged in society
and i also have difficulty seeing these
very disparate groups that are the
the immigrants organizing as
such um they tend to organize
according to the lines of ethnic uh
ethnicities and so
um what i mean rather
is um that okay
a lot of us work outside of the
of the norms and the habits and
functions
of the the modern labor market
and as such we have a shared
interest with unemployed people
and people who don't quite fit in and
these this group in itself cannot
organize itself
for logical reasons because
everybody wants to stop being unemployed
and
skip out
out of that out of that hole right
so rather it's that
if uh metamodernists and the quadruple
age population
build a more listening society with
basic uh
support structures for everyone not
necessarily ubi but other
forms that don't have you jumping
through all the modern hoops
then there's likely to be a quiet
support
from somewhere from well from the
precarious
from the people who would like to be
supported
in living lives that don't quite fit in
into the modern framework and more and
more people are
falling into that category due to the
pressures of globalization
and and of course digitization
right thank you daniel i think we did
two hours now and i think that's the
perfect
point to close this lecture for today
thank you all for participating and to
be here and partake on this discussion
thank you daniel
for taking the time thank you
um yeah i hope you will all tune in next
time
our next lectures will be raul effelmann
the
creator of the aforementioned
performative
performatism he will come on this
program
thursday you can see that on the
parallax website
and so we have a nice lineup coming up
again thank you all for participating i
wish you all a very
great evening and see you soon bye